This video demonstrates how to perform a distance and near-visual acuity test.
Wash your hands and don't PPE.
You will need the arclight charts and a safety pin to make pinholes.
The room must be quiet and at least three meters wide.
It should be well lit, ideally with natural light.
If you're outside, make sure the sun is on the patient's back, shining onto the chart.
The patient should be seated comfortably, although standing is okay.
Show the patient the chart at arm's length, ask them to point in the
direction at the
ease point.
Check the patient understands and you're both happy to start.
If the patient
normally wears glasses for distance, use them for the test.
If not, then test unaided.
They
should cover one eye with a pan with their hand, not their fingers.
Place the chart at
the same level as the patient's eyes at a distance of 3 metres.
Start with the largest
letters at the top of the chart working downwards.
Stop the test when the patient can no longer
correctly indicate the direction of the ease or they complete the test.
Now record the
acuity achieved.
The left side of the chart is labelled in Snellen notation with log mar
on the right.
Snellen is recorded as a fraction with a test distance on top and the last full
line seen correctly on the bottom.
If some of the next line was also seen then right plus
one or plus two for extra letters seen.
For a log mar again record the last full line
read correctly but this time subtract 0.07 if they managed one extra letter correctly
or 0.14 if they saw two.
If the patient cannot see even the biggest
e at 3 metres then half the distance to 1.5 metres.
If they still cannot see at this distance
then test if they can count your fingers, follow your hand movements or if
they can perceive
light.
Record what they could see and the distance.
If the patient's vision is reduced, less than 3 over 3 or log mar
0, then also test with
a pinhole.
This can show if the vision is reduced due to lack of glasses.
You can make a set of pinholes by pushing a pin through the near
card where the black
dots are.
Ask the patient to hold the card over the eye you are testing while
covering their other eye with
their palm.
They will need to move it up or down a little so they can see through at least one hole.
Repeat distance testing with the pinhole and record the results, making it clear that this test
was with a pinhole.
Now test near visual acuity.
Ask the patient to hold the chart 40 centimeters
away at a typical reading angle.
If they own reading glasses test with them on.
If not, then test
unaided.
Aspen to keep both eyes open this time.
Explain that you want them to read out loud,
starting with the biggest letters at the top of the chart.
If the patient cannot read well,
then aspen to point to small words or certain letters such as O, name
letters in the words,
match letters to a matching card or copy the shapes of letters in the
ear with their finger.
Stop the test when the patient can no longer read accurately and comfortably.
Record the number
of the last line they saw clearly.
If their near vision is worse than N8, then repeat with
reading glasses of different powers.